Guide to the Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers [Guía a los materiales de Ramón Gómez de la Serna], 1906-1967 SC.1967.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers [Ramón Gómez de la Serna Escritos]
1906-1967
1936-1963
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Gómez de la Serna, Ramón
SC.1967.04
27 Linear Feet (45 boxes)
Ramón Gómez de la Serna was a prolific Spanish poet, novelist, and essayist, who is especially known for creating a new literary genre he named the "greguería." His works significantly influenced the avant-garde movement in Europe and Latin America. His personal papers consist of approximately 60,000 handwritten notes and manuscripts, clippings, photographs, and annotated first editions from his library from 1906-1967. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online. Ramón Gómez de la Serna fue un prolífico poeta, novelista y ensayista hispano, especialmente conocido por crear un nuevo género literario al que llamó la "greguería". Sus obras influyeron significativamente en el movimiento de vanguardia en Europa y América Latina. Sus documentos personales consisten en aproximadamente 60,000 notas escritas a mano y manuscritos, recortes, fotografías y primeras ediciones anotadas de su biblioteca de 1906-1967. Las reproducciones digitales de partes de la colección están disponibles en línea.
Biography [Biografía]
Ramón Gómez de la Serna Puig was born in 1888 in Madrid, Spain, and died in Buenos Aires, Argentina, in 1963. His father, Javier Gomez de la Serna and Laguna, was a lawyer, and his mother, Josefa Puig Coronado, was the niece of the romantic Spanish poet Carolina Coronado. Ramón studied law as well but never worked professionally in the field. In 1905, he published his first work entitled "Entrando en fuego." In 1908, with the support of his father, he founded the literary journal Prometeo. In addition, Ramón wrote for Spanish newspapers such as El Sol, La Voz, and Revista de Occidente, where he was noted for his original character, leading an imaginative and sometimes nihilistic rebellion against a society that he perceived as culturally stagnant. He launched a literary circle in the Café Pombo in Madrid in 1912, where he gathered with other artists and intellectuals such as Tomás Borrás, Manuel Abril, José Bergamín, and José Gutiérrez Solana. At the age of twenty-one, he began an enduring and influential relationship with the early feminist writer Carmen de Burgos, who was twenty years his senior. This relationship inspired the novel La viuda blanca y negra [The Black and White Widow] (1921).
As early as 1910, Ramón began experimenting with a new literary art form he called the "greguería." Ramón himself defined the greguería as a mathematical equation: Greguería = Humor + Metaphor. Others have characterized it as a brief, humorous insight expressed in metaphoric language. With his innovative and iconoclastic approach, Ramón had a strong influence on the Spanish avant-garde, the surrealist movement, and on the later 1927 generation of poets and writers.
In the early 1930s, Ramón developed an interest in visiting South America, and an invitation to give some lectures in Argentina provided him with this opportunity. During his first trip, he met his later wife, Luisa Sofovich, in Buenos Aires. Back in the Spain, the outbreak of the Civil War in 1936 surprised him in Madrid. Soon after, he decided to leave for self-exile to Argentina where he remained until his death.
Ramón Gómez de la Serna Puig nació en 1888 en Madrid, España y murió en Buenos Aires, Argentina en 1963. Su padre, Javier Gómez de la Serna y Laguna era abogado, y su madre, Josefa Puig Coronado era sobrina de la poeta romántica española Carolina Coronado. Ramón también estudió derecho pero nunca trabajó profesionalmente en ese campo. En 1905 publicó su primer trabajo titulado "Entrando en fuego". En 1908 fundó la revista literaria "Prometeo" con el apoyo de su padre. Además, Ramón escribió para periódicos españoles como El Sol, La Voz y "Revista de Occidente", donde se destacó por su carácter original, liderando una rebelión imaginativa y a veces nihilista contra una sociedad que percibió como culturalmente estancada. Lanzó un círculo literario en el "Café Pombo" de Madrid en 1912, donde se reunió con otros artistas e intelectuales como Tomás Borrás, Manuel Abril, José Bergamín y José Gutiérrez Solana. A la edad de veintiún años comenzó una relación duradera e influyente con la escritora feminista temprana Carmen de Burgos, quien era veinte años mayor que él. Esta relación inspiró la novela "La viuda blanca y negra" (1921).
En 1910 Ramón comenzó a experimentar con una nueva forma de arte literario que llamó la "greguería". El propio Ramón definió la greguería como una ecuación matemática: Greguería = Humor + Metáfora. Otros lo han caracterizado como una visión breve y humorística expresada en lenguaje metafórico. Con su enfoque innovador e iconoclasta, Ramón tuvo una fuerte influencia en la vanguardia española, el movimiento surrealista y en la generación posterior de poetas y escritores de 1927.
A principios de la década de 1930, Ramón desarrolló un interés en visitar América del Sur y una invitación para dar algunas conferencias en Argentina le brindó esta oportunidad. Durante su primer viaje, conoció en Buenos Aires a Luisa Sofovich quien posteriormente fue su esposa. De vuelta en España, el estallido de la Guerra Civil en 1936 lo sorprendió en Madrid. Poco después decidió partir para el autoexilio a Argentina, donde permaneció hasta su muerte.
Scope and Content Notes [Notas de Alcance y Contenido]
The Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers consist of approximately 60,000 mostly handwritten notes and manuscripts, which represent the core of the collection. They also include photographs, clippings, and annotated first editions of his published writings. While the collection spans the date ranges between 1906-1967, the bulk of the material dates between 1936-1963.
The manuscripts cover all genres of his literary output such as greguerías, novels, biographies, art books, humoristic pieces, short stories, and dramas. The majority of the documents are undated. They can be found under the "Writings" series, subdivided by the genre, and then by the individual work itself. Ramón also used an extensive amount of clippings from newspapers, magazines, and books for artistic inspiration and research on his projects.
A smaller part of the papers consists of correspondence (e.g. with the dramatist Enrique Jardiel Poncela, Ernesto Bustamante, and Luis de Olarra). Most of the correspondence can be found in the correspondence series; however, in some cases the biographies subseries holds correspondence as well, for example in the case of Macedonio Fernández and Gutiérrez Solana.
Furthermore, the papers feature photographs and personal documents, such as posthumous clippings by Luisa Sofovich on Ramón's life and work, educational and legal certificates, as well as address books. Please note that most of the material is sparsely dated, therefore date-ranges could often not be established for folder contents.
Los documentos de Ramón Gómez de la Serna consisten en aproximadamente 60,000 notas y manuscritos, que representan el núcleo de la colección. También incluyen fotografías, recortes y primeras ediciones anotadas de sus escritos publicados. Si bien la colección abarca los rangos de fechas entre 1906-1967, la mayor parte del material data entre 1936-1963.
Los manuscritos cubren todos los géneros de su producción literaria, como greguerías, novelas, biografías, libros de arte, piezas humorísticas, cuentos y dramas. La mayoría de los documentos no tienen fecha. Se pueden encontrar en la serie "Escritos", subdividida por el género, y luego por el trabajo individual en sí. Ramón también utilizó una gran cantidad de recortes de periódicos, revistas y libros para inspiración artística e investigación sobre sus proyectos.
Una parte más pequeña de los documentos consiste en correspondencia (por ejemplo, con el dramaturgo Enrique Jardiel Poncela, Ernesto Bustamante y Luis de Olarra). La mayor parte de la correspondencia se puede encontrar en la serie de correspondencia; sin embargo, en algunos casos la subserie de biografías también mantiene correspondencia, por ejemplo en el caso de Macedonio Fernández y Gutiérrez Solana.
Además, los documentos presentan fotografías y documentos personales, como recortes póstumos de Luisa Sofovich sobre la vida y el trabajo de Ramón, sus certificados educativos y legales, así como sus libretas de direcciones. Se debe tener en cuenta que la mayor parte del material está escasamente fechado, por lo tanto, los intervalos de fechas a menudo no se pueden establecer en el contenido de la carpeta.
Access Restrictions [Restricciones de Acceso]
No restrictions.
Sin restricciones.
Arrangement [Arreglo]
The papers are organized according to the following series:
Series I. Biographical and Personal Material Series II. Writings Series III. Correspondence Series IV. Clippings
Los documentos están organizados según las siguientes series:
Serie I. Material biográfico y personal Serie II. Escritos Serie III. Correspondencia Serie IV. Recortes de prensa
Acquisition Information [Información de Adquisición]
Aquired from Ramón Gómez de la Serna's widow, Luisa Sofovich, on April 1, 1967.
Adquirido de la viuda de Ramón Gómez de la Serna, Luisa Sofovich, el 1 de abril de 1967.
Related Materials [Materiales Relacionados]
Please note that the books of Ramón Gómez de la Serna's library are cataloged with the book holdings of Special Collections. They can be located by doing a TITLE search "Ramón Gómez de la Serna papers, 1906-1967." Click on the "ULS Digital Collections" to access the "Guide to the Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers, 1906-1967"
Tenga en cuenta que los libros de la biblioteca de Ramón Gómez de la Serna están catalogados con los fondos de libros de Colecciones Especiales. Se pueden localizar haciendo una búsqueda de TÍTULO "Papeles de Ramón Gómez de la Serna, 1906-1967". Al hacer clic en "Colecciones digitales ULS" se accede a la "Guía de los trabajos de Ramón Gómez de la Serna, 1906-1967".
Existence and Location of Copies [Existencia y Ubicación de Copias]
Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available within the finding aid.
Las reproducciones digitales de partes de la colección están disponibles dentro de la ayuda de búsqueda.
Previous Citation [ Cita Anterior]
Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers, 1906-1967, SC.1967.04, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers, 1906-1967, SC.1967.04, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh.
Madrid (Spain); Buenos Aires (Argentina); Authors, Spanish American -- 20th century; Authors, Spanish -- 20th century; Literature, Experimental; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Aphorisms and apothegms; Aphorisms and apothegms in literature; Manuscripts for publication; Manuscripts (Document genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Personal papers; Ortega y Gasset, José; Sofovich, Luisa; Gómez de la Serna, Ramón; Fernández, Macedonio; Coronado, Carolina
- Biographical and Personal Material [Material biográfico y personal], 1906-1966; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series comprises a variety of documents reflecting Ramón's personal life, consisting of educational and medical documents, awards, posthumous clippings, and photographs. The series is divided into four subseries, each representing those different areas.
  Esta serie comprende una variedad de documentos que reflejan la vida personal de Ramón, que consta de documentos educativos y médicos, premios, recortes póstumos y fotografías. La serie se divide en cuatro subseries, cada una representando esas diferentes áreas.
  - Biographical Documents [Documentos biográficos], 1906-1958; 1.
    This subseries consists mostly of Ramón's biographical documents, such as his certificate of baptism, passport, identity card, law degree diploma from the Universidad de Oviedo, correspondence from the Spanish Ministry of Justice referring to Ramón's employment in the administration. Also found here are two address notebooks listing the writer's friends and acquaintances from an early date, including artistic and literary people prominent in the 1920s.
    Esta subserie consiste principalmente en los documentos biográficos de Ramón, como su certificado de bautismo, pasaporte, documento de identidad, diploma de abogado de la Universidad de Oviedo, correspondencia del Ministerio de Justicia español que se refiere al empleo de Ramón en la administración. También se encuentran aquí dos cuadernos de direcciones que enumeran los amigos y conocidos del escritor desde una fecha temprana, incluidas las personas artísticas y literarias prominentes en la década de 1920.
    - Ministry of Justice Correspondence, 1906-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificates, 1949 and 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ID Card (Argentina) and Passport (Spain), 1936 and 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Address Books: "Francia, Paris" and Other (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "El postal": First Book Authored by Ramón, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Enfermedad Ramón, 1958-1962; 2.
    Ramón's own notes, medical reports, and clippings document the effects of certain drugs and his weight loss. Discussed are also a philosophy of death and illness, antidotes for poisons, and the effects of drugs on illness.
    Las propias notas, informes médicos y recortes de Ramón documentan los efectos de ciertas drogas y su pérdida de peso. Se discuten también una filosofía de muerte y enfermedad, antídotos para venenos y los efectos de las drogas sobre la enfermedad.
    - Loose Notes, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lab Reports, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Regimen": Notes on Diet and Prescriptions, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Premio Madrid, 1962; 3.
    This subseries features material on a literary award won by Gómez de la Serna in 1962 named "Premio Madrid" by the Juan March Foundation.
    Esta subserie presenta material sobre un premio literario ganado por Gómez de la Serna en 1962 llamado "Premio Madrid" por la Fundación Juan March.
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Artículos Necrológicos, 1938-1966; 4.
    This subseries represents an extensive collection of newspaper clippings about Gómez de la Serna, apparently compiled by Luisa Sofovich, featuring primarily obituaries or reviews of his life and work, some of the latter published before his death.
    Esta subserie representa una extensa colección de recortes de periódico sobre Gómez de la Serna, aparentemente compilada por Luisa Sofovich, que presenta principalmente obituarios o reseñas de su vida y obra, algunos de estos últimos publicados antes de su muerte.
    - Newspaper Clippings, Authors A-J, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Authors K-Z, 1938-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Unidentified Author, 1940-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Images, and Graphic Items on Funeral, Drawings, Death Notices, 1960, 1963, and undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Images, and Graphic Items on Funeral, Drawings, Death Notices, 1960, 1963, and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Radio Broadcast Transcription of a Posthumous Homage to Ramón Gómez de la Serna from L.S.1. Radio Municipal de la Ciudad de Buenos Aires, January 13, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Unidentified Fragments (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, "Reproducciones de fotos de Ramón y Luisita," [Fotografías, "Reproducciones de fotos de Ramón y Luisita,"], 1931-1955; 5.
    The photographs show Ramón at various ages, in his study, with others, and together with Luisa Sofovich. Luisa Sofovich herself is depicted in several images, as well as photographic reproductions of artwork featuring Ramón, and clippings of drawings and caricatures representing Ramón.
    Las fotografías muestran a Ramón a varias edades, en su estudio, con otros y junto con Luisa Sofovich. La propia Luisa Sofovich se representa en varias imágenes, así como en reproducciones fotográficas de obras de arte con Ramón, y recortes de dibujos y caricaturas que representan a Ramón.
    - Ramón (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ramón in His Study (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ramón and Others (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Ramón and Luisa Sofovich, 1931-1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Luisa Sofovich (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photographic Reproductions of Artistic Representations of Ramón (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clippings of Drawings and Caricatures Representing Ramón (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Writings [Escritos], II.
  As the core of the papers, Ramón's writings represent the whole spectrum of his literary output such as novels, biographies, short stories, journalism, and of course, greguerías. This series is subdivided into subseries according to genre, and then organized into sections according to the title of the individual work if applicable.
  Como núcleo de los documentos, los escritos de Ramón representan todo el espectro de su producción literaria, como novelas, biografías, cuentos, periodismo y, por supuesto, greguerías. Esta serie se subdivide en subseries según el género, y luego se organiza en secciones según el título del trabajo individual, si corresponde.
  - Greguerías, 1949-1962; 1.
    This subseries compiles a wide range of material documenting Ramón's creative work, research, and interest in greguerías, including his own drawings to illustrate greguerías, demonstrating the graphic aspect of the genre; his lecture notes and scripts for public presentations; anthologies of phrases and sayings in related style selected from a wide range of authors; his notes and explorations into associated subject areas such as humor and the metaphor; and a compilation of heavily annotated manuscript pages and clippings of his greguerías for a future book project.
    Esta subserie recopila una amplia gama de material que documenta el trabajo creativo, la investigación y el interés de Ramón en las greguerías, incluidos sus propios dibujos para ilustrar las greguerías, demostrando el aspecto gráfico del género; sus apuntes y guiones para presentaciones públicas; antologías de frases y dichos en estilo relacionado seleccionados de una amplia gama de autores; sus notas y exploraciones en áreas temáticas asociadas como el humor y la metáfora; y una compilación de páginas manuscritas muy anotadas y recortes de sus greguerías para un futuro proyecto de libro.
    - Loose Greguería Notes and Unidentified Fragments (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Loose Greguería Notes (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Conferencia Greguería," Lecture Notes (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Porqué se llaman greguerías," Lecture Notes (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Nueva explicación de las greguerías," Typescript (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Radioscript by Ramón on Greguerías, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Clippings on the Subject of "Metáforas" by Various Authors (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Prólogo – Greguería": Greguerías and Notes about Greguerías by Ramón (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Humoristic Notes by Ramón and Others (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Humoristic Notes by Ramón and Others (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Clippings of Humoristic Sayings by Ramón and Others (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Il «Refranero» attribuito al Marqués Santillana," by G.M. Bertini, Clipping of Published Article, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Greguerías illustradas, Items 1-95 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Greguerías illustradas, Items 96-133 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 1-80 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 81-165 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 166-248 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 1-81 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 82-156 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 1-64 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 1-90 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 91-176 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Gregues:" Compilation of Phrases from a Range of Authors, Items 1-62 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Clarín Gregues": Clippings of Ramón's Published Greguerías from ABC, Clarín, and Maybe Other Publications (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Greguerías últimas escogidas", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1958-1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro" (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1958-1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Nuevas greguerías: Inéditas en libro", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Annotated Published Greguería Clippings (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Novels [Novelas], 2.
    This subseries documents Ramón's work as a novelist. It is divided into sections to reflect a specific subgenre, such as short stories (novelas cortas), or a specific work.
    Esta subserie documenta el trabajo de Ramón como novelista. Se divide en secciones para reflejar un subgénero específico, como cuentos cortos (novelas cortas) o un trabajo específico.
    - Novelas Cortas
      This section contains a collection of the author's published short stories, most of them in form of clippings of the original pages of the paperback first editions.
      Esta sección contiene una colección de cuentos publicados por el autor, la mayoría en forma de recortes de las páginas originales de las primeras ediciones en rústica.
      - "La abandonada en el Rastro" (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "Aquella novela" (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "La donna de Kikir" (Italian Version of "La Fúnebre") (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - "Los dos marineros" (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - "Ella & Ella – El & El" (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - "La fúnebre" (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - "La gallipava" (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - "La gangosa" (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - "Leopoldo y Teresa" (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - "El joven de las sobremesas" (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "La malicia de las acacias" (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "Maria Yarsilovna" (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - "El miedo al mar" (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "La mujer vestida de hombre" (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - "El olor de las mimosas" (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - "El regalo al doctor" (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - "A ruiva" (Portuguese Version of "La roja") translated by Rogerio García Pérez (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - "La saturada" (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - "La tormenta" (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - "El turco de los nardos" and "El vegetariano" (title page only) (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Hombre de alambre
      This section contains drafts, fragments, and notes for the until recently unpublished novel El Hombre de alambre illustrating the early stages of Ramón's creative process. Most of the drafts form a complete narrative or dialogue in themselves but the linking material and the development of the novel as a whole are still lacking. The central character is an old and lonely emigrant whose personality is constructed through the metaphor of wire. Disillusioned, he metaphorically transforms his essential being into wires in order to make himself immune to sorrow. As death approaches, he begins an interior dialogue in which he finds the meaning of life and reconciles himself both to himself and to the idea of death, finally dying in a state of peace.